Indeed, there is no end to the search for strength.
武道确实学无止境
You are one step closer to finding the secret.
你离悟出奥义又更进一步了
There is nothing left for me to teach you.
我已经没有什么可以教你的了
You tell me that every day.
你每天都是这么说的
Oh, Fern?
咦 菲伦？
Pout…
唔…
She's angry? Why?
她气呼呼的？为什么？
I'm scared.
好可怕啊
ORIGINAL STORY BY KANEHITO YAMADA / TSUKASA ABE
（原作：山田钟人 作画：阿部司）
I had a fight with Mistress Frieren.
我跟芙莉莲大人吵架了
Again? This has been happening a lot lately.
又吵架了？ 最近是不是吵得有点多啊？
The upcoming third stage is the final stage of the exam, right?
第三阶段考试 就是最后一轮考试了吧？
This is no time to be fighting.
哪里还有时间吵架？
This time, she has crossed the line.
这次她太过分了
My staff broke during the battle in the Ruins of the King's Tomb,
在零落王墓战斗时 我的法杖毁坏了
so I told Mistress Frieren that I wanted to get it repaired.
所以我告诉芙莉莲大人我想送去修理
But she told me that I should throw away
但她却告诉我
my old staff and buy a new one.
丢掉旧法杖 买新的就好
That staff?
是那支法杖吧
She said it was shattered and can't be fixed.
她说坏成那样已经修不好了
But still,
就算是这样
I received that staff from Master Heiter.
那也是海塔大人送我的法杖
I've had it ever since I was small.
从我还小的时候 就一直陪在我身边了
You know how Frieren is. She didn't mean to hurt you.
毕竟是芙莉莲啊 她不是有意的
For me, the thought of
我可是从来没有
throwing it away never even crossed my mind.
动过把它丢掉的念头啊
The next first-class mage exam is three years from now, huh?
下次的一级魔法使测验是三年后啊？
Three years is a long time.
三年真的很久呢
Go ahead and laugh at me, like usual.
你就像以往那样笑我啊
You want me to laugh at you?
你希望我笑你吗？
No.
没有
Well then, little Lawine, want me to pat you on the head?
那小拉比涅 要不要我摸摸头啊？
You want to fight?
想打架吗？
Hurry up.
快点摸啦
She's really taking it hard.
还真的是耿耿于怀呢
Oh, it's Frieren.
喔 是芙莉莲
What's that bag?
那个袋子里装了什么东西？
Hey.
喂
How long are you going to stay here?
是打算在这里逛多久啊？
I failed the exam. We have nothing to do with each other anymore.
我考试没过 彼此已经是陌路人了吧
You're interfering with my business. Go away.
你们已经妨碍到我做生意了 快滚
I am here as a customer right now.
老夫现在是以客人的身分来的
Then hurry up and pick something.
那就赶紧挑东西
-You can have it. -Keep it.
-给 -不用了
You were out of luck this time.
这次你的运气不好
The situation was not in our favor.
刚好遇上不利的情况
Everybody who was there could have ended up like you.
不管换成是谁 下场都会跟你一样
Either way, I still failed. I didn't have enough skill.
没过就是没过 是我技不如人
Don't bring this subject up again.
所以不要再提起这件事了
I may not look it, but I am in the worst mood.
也许表面上看不出来 但我的心情很糟
And yet you still opened your shop.
尽管如此 你还是开门营业了啊
Denken, this may come as a surprise to you,
邓肯 你也许不知道吧
but no matter how bad their mood is,
但是一个人心情再怎么糟
people need to work to put food on the table.
为了生存还是得出门赚钱啊
I see.
这样啊
Well, it's a good thing that I was the one who dropped out.
不过 其实是我不合格也好
First-class mage exams are once in three years.
一级魔法使选拔每三年一次
Denken,
邓肯
for a feeble old man like you, that time may never come.
你这样的老头子 能不能还有下一个三年都不知道呢
True.
确实如此
At least try to retort.
回嘴啊
Richter, you really are an impudent little punk.
利希塔 你真是个肆无忌惮的臭小子
You disrespect authority and are willing to
不把权威放在眼里 而且
mistreat the weak for the sake of fulfilling your purpose.
为达目的 不惜残害弱者
You are definitely no saint.
就是个彻头彻尾的坏蛋呢
Despite that, I don't have any ill feelings toward you.
就算如此 老夫也没有厌恶你的感受
That is probably
很可能是因为
because I used to be an impudent little punk myself.
我以前就是个肆无忌惮的臭小子吧
But look at me now.
但那样的我
I am now an Imperial Mage.
如今也当上宫廷魔法使了
What are you trying to say?
你究竟想说什么？
What I mean is, you don't have to be so pessimistic.
我想说的是 你不用那么悲观
Three years from now, you will be much stronger than you are now.
三年后的你会比现在强更多
Let's go, Laufen.
拉奥芬 回去吧
Sorry. That old man isn't good at expressing his feelings.
不好意思啊 老爷子他这个人就是嘴笨
What is your relationship with him anyway?
你到底是邓肯的谁啊？
That old fart…
臭老头子
In the end, he didn't even buy anything.
结果什么东西都没买嘛
Today is really not my day, is it?
今天难道是我犯冲吗？
I asked around town, and everyone said that
我在城里四处打听过了 大家都说
you would be able to repair any staff, no matter how broken it is.
不管东西坏成什么样子 你都修得好
Let me see.
给我看看
What are all these pieces?
这些碎片是什么？
Don't tell me this is a staff.
不会是法杖吧？
What am I supposed to do with this trash?
拿这种垃圾给我 我又能怎么样？
It's not trash…
这不是垃圾…
I think.
大概吧
I was starting to feel a little better,
我本来心情开始好一点了
but now I'm back to being in a horrible mood because of you.
拜你所赐 现在又跌到谷底了
I have the right to choose my jobs.
我也有选择工作的权利
Just give up on this staff.
这个法杖不要了吧
I see.
这样啊
If you're unable to fix it, it's okay.
你要是修不好就算了
Frieren, you sure know how to get on my nerves, don't you?
芙莉莲 你真的很擅长惹毛别人耶
When did I ever say I was unable to do it?
我什么时候说过修不好了？
Can you finish it by today?
今天之内可以修好吗？
I want it ready by the third stage of the exam.
不然会赶不上第三阶段考试
What an unreasonable request.
真是过分的要求
-Frieren. -What?
-芙莉莲 -怎么了？
I'm sorry for calling it trash.
我为刚刚说它是垃圾的事道歉
It's a nice, well-maintained staff.
这根法杖受到仔细的保养
I can tell the owner really treasured it.
看得出来法杖的主人很珍惜它
Fern, let's go back already.
菲伦 该回去了吧
Mistress Frieren doesn't understand me at all.
芙莉莲大人根本就不懂我
Well, I don't understand you either.
那种事就连我也不懂啊
Stop it! Don't take it out on me!
不要啊 别冲着我发火啊！
In my opinion,
所以说
that is why it's important to try to understand.
试着去理解对方也很重要
I think Frieren is doing her best.
我觉得芙莉莲很努力在理解你了
Oh, you're Frieren's…
哦 你是芙莉莲的…
apprentice, right?
徒弟 是吧？
Am I wrong?
我弄错了吗？
No, you're right.
没有 你说得没错
Well, I couldn't care less either way.
是不是我都无所谓了
The second stage just ended,
第二阶段考试才刚结束
and I'm already being overworked because of your master.
我就因为你师父不得不加班工作
It would have been better for my business
她要是干脆买支新的
if she had just bought a new one.
我还比较好赚呢
Take good care of it.
好好珍惜哦
SWALLOW INN
（斯瓦洛旅店）
My staff…
我的法杖…
Frieren lacks emotions and sensibility.
芙莉莲欠缺感情与感性
I'm sure that will lead to difficulties and misunderstandings.
肯定会造成沟通困难跟误解
But there is also one good thing about it.
不过这也有一个好处
To make up for what she lacks,
为了弥补这个缺点
Frieren will spend more time worrying about you.
她一定会为了你费尽心思
You're not going to find another master like her that easily.
很难找到比她更好的师父了
It's dark…
好黑啊…
Um, Mistress Frieren, about yesterday…
那个 芙莉莲大人 昨天…
What?
怎么了？
Never mind. It's nothing.
没有 还是不要说好了
Okay.
是喔
We will now begin the third stage of the exam.
那么 我宣布现在开始第三阶段考试
Do you know the reason why I came
你知道我为什么
all the way here, Sense?
要特地来这里吗？
You're not going to answer?
不回答吗？
This is how you are whenever things become inconvenient.
每次苗头不对的时候 你就会沉默以对呢
There were 12 people who passed the second stage.
第二阶段有十二名考生合格
That is an unprecedented number. It's too many.
以前从未有过这个数字 太多人了
I don't mind exams where everybody joins forces.
以全员分工合作的方式 进行考试是没关系
The existing first-class mages lack a sense of cooperation, after all.
毕竟现有的一级魔法使 缺乏的正是合作能力
I'm afraid that's true.
真是惭愧
But among them
但是考生之中
was one person with too much power.
有一位实力超群的人物
You mean Mistress Frieren?
您是指芙莉莲大人吧？
Thanks to that, many inadequate people were able to pass as well.
很多没有实力的人 都是因为她才能合格
If they go onto the third stage as scheduled,
如果他们像以往那样 去参加第三阶段的考试
they will all die.
会全军覆没的
Sense,
赞泽
that's not even close to what you desire.
这跟你原本所希望的结果相反吧
And even I don't want
而且即便是我
to waste the lives of this many people.
也不想造成这么多无意义的伤亡
Mistress Serie…
赛丽艾大人…
You don't have to apologize.
你不必道歉
It's all Frieren's fault.
这全是芙莉莲的错
We'll make an exception this time.
既然情况不同 就以特例处理
I will take care of the third stage.
第三阶段考试就由我来主持
I'll select them in a peaceful way.
就用和平的方式来筛选吧
You were in charge of it originally, right?
按照惯例 以前都是你负责吧？
You don't mind, do you, Lernen?
你没有异议吧 莱尔恩？
This isn't my first time
赛丽艾大人也不是
being at the mercy of your one-sided decisions.
第一次略过我下决定了
Plus,
况且
I am not at a level where I can test Mistress Frieren.
我也没有资格能够测试芙莉莲大人
Just one glance, and I knew
我见到她的第一眼便明白了
that she was suppressing her mana.
她在抑制自身的魔力
She has an enormous amount of mana.
她的魔力无可比拟
It is on par with you, Mistress Serie.
已经可以媲美赛丽艾大人了
Falsch, did you notice?
法尔修 你有注意到吗？
No, I don't know what he's talking about.
没有 我其实不太明白他在说什么
I saw her mana with my own eyes at the exam hall.
我在考试会场亲眼看过她的魔力
I highly doubt that her mana was suppressed.
一点也不觉得她有抑制魔力的情形
It didn't even have the characteristic of instability of suppressed mana.
连抑制魔力特有的晃动都没有
All living organisms with mana have this instability
只要是拥有魔力的生物 都免不了这种晃动
and it cannot be stopped.
那是不可能消除的
Even if that is possible,
就算真的有可能做到
it'd take an exorbitant amount of time.
肯定是花了长到离谱的时间在修行吧
It is by no means a practical skill.
不管怎么样 这都不是很实用的技术
Frieren dedicated her entire life to this so-called unpractical skill.
芙莉莲就是在这种不实用的技术上 倾注了一生的时光
In order to deceive demons.
为的就是要欺骗魔族
Demons are far more sensitive to mana than mankind.
魔族的魔力感知比人类还敏锐
Unless you're some kind of prodigy,
不是天赋奇才的话
you wouldn't be able to deceive them just by suppressing
单纯只是抑制魔力一、两百年
your mana for 100 or 200 years.
是骗不过他们的
It's literally a waste of time.
实在是浪费时间
Using that time on other training would make you
把那些时间拿去锻炼其他方面
significantly stronger.
都不知道会变强几倍
It's completely inefficient.
一点效率都没有
However,
但是
such inefficiency can open up a window of opportunity.
这样没有效率的做法 也能制造对手的破绽
When it comes to battles between skilled mages,
身经百战的魔法使对战
miscalculating your opponent's mana can lead to your death.
误判对方的魔力就可能丧命
Frieren is living proof.
芙莉莲就是活生生的证明
Her level of skill is low for someone her age,
以她的年纪而言 她的技术水准很低
but she's been defeating demons this way.
但她就是这样打倒魔族的
That is how precise Frieren's mana suppression is.
芙莉莲的魔力抑制就是如此熟练
As far as I know,
据我所知
the Demon King is the only one who noticed in one glance.
至今为止 能一眼识破她伪装的就只有魔王
At least, that's what I thought up until now, Lernen.
现在能瞬间识破她的人 还多了你莱尔恩
It was a coincidence.
纯粹是偶然
I happened to see the slightest instability.
我偶然看到了轻微的晃动
That's all.
仅此而已
You're so modest and dependable.
还真是谦虚稳重呢
It's been half a century since you became the very first
自从你当上一级魔法使以来
first-class mage.
都已经过了半世纪了
You are still the same timid boy you used to be.
但你依旧是以往那个胆小的小男孩呢
And that's why it's such a shame.
这点真是令人遗憾
You've made it this far, and yet you
难得你已经走到这一步
don't have much longer to live.
生命时光却已所剩无几了
You probably will never have the chance to battle Frieren.
你余生可能也没有机会 跟芙莉莲对战了
Even if it's a battle you can possibly win.
尽管你有可能打赢她
I really shouldn't take in any human apprentices.
果然不该培养人类的弟子啊
It's such a shame…
真的是太遗憾了…
In the end, not even he could notice the instability
结果连那孩子也无法察觉到
of my mana, huh?
我魔力的晃动吗？
The third stage of the exam
第三阶段考试
will be an interview with the Great Mage Serie.
是大魔法使赛丽艾的面试
I didn't expect that.
真是出乎我的意料
Serie has no intention of letting us pass.
赛丽艾不想让我跟菲伦通过吧
You know her?
您认识她吗？
From a long time ago.
已经是很久以前的事了
She's probably going to choose who passes by instinct.
她大概是想用直觉选出合格者吧
But Serie's instincts are always right.
不过赛丽艾的直觉向来都很准
As proof of that,
就拿我来说
I still haven't become the mage that Serie wants me to be.
我至今也没有成为 赛丽艾希望的那种魔法使
-Excuse me. -You fail. Go home.
-那个… -不合格 回去
Can I ask why?
可以告诉我理由吗？
Right now, you are afraid of my mana.
现在的你对我的魔力感到恐惧
You are well aware of your limits.
你其实很清楚自己的实力到哪
You can't visualize yourself as a first-class mage, can you?
你还无法想象自己 成为一级魔法使的样子吧？
In the world of magic,
在魔法的世界里
you can't actualize it if you can't visualize it.
无法想象的事情是不会实现的
That's the basic principle. Go home.
这是基本中的基本 出去
Fail. Fail.
不合格
Frieren,
芙莉莲
you also can't visualize yourself as a first-class mage, can you?
你也无法想象自己 当上一级魔法使的样子吧？
But the reason is different from the other examinees.
但是你不合格的原因与其他考生不同
You are absolutely sure that I'm not going to let you pass.
你根本不认为我会让你合格
It's the truth, right?
那是事实吧？
I will give you one chance.
我再给你一次机会
Tell me a spell you like.
告诉我你喜欢的魔法
The spell to create a field of flowers.
变出花田的魔法
You learned that from Flamme, huh?
是伏拉梅教你的吗？
How stupid. You fail.
有够无聊 不合格
Okay.
这样啊
You're not going to stand your ground even after being ridiculed?
即使被耍了 也不打算为自己辩护吗？
It's hard to believe that a mage
实在难以相信
like you was able to defeat the Demon King.
像你这样的魔法使居然能打倒魔王
I didn't do it alone.
那不是我自己一个人的功劳
Himmel, Eisen, Heiter, and me.
辛美尔、艾泽、海塔还有我
If even one of us was missing, we couldn't have done it.
少了一个就做不到这件事了
You were blessed with good comrades?
是托了伙伴的福吗？
How lucky of you.
运气真好呢
That's right.
是啊
I was lucky.
我运气不错
Himmel,
喂 辛美尔
why did you invite me into the party?
你为什么邀请我当伙伴呢？
Because I was looking for a strong mage.
因为我在找很厉害的魔法使啊
There are a bunch of them in the royal capital.
那样的话 王都里随便找都有
It didn't have to be me.
不一定非我不可吧
I wanted you.
我就要你
Why?
为什么？
Frieren, you probably don't remember,
芙莉莲 你大概不记得了
but I've met you once in the past.
但是很久以前我见过你一次
Yeah, I don't remember at all.
嗯 我完全不记得了
I figured.
我想也是
When I was a kid, I entered a forest to pick herbs
我还小的时候 曾进去森林里采药
and got lost.
结果迷路了
For a while, I was wandering around the forest at night.
我在夜晚的森林里 四处游荡了一段时间
For the first time in my life, I experienced solitude.
人生中第一次体会到了孤独
I thought I would never be able to return to the village.
我以为我再也回不了村子了
But then
那个时候
an elf pointed to the direction of civilization.
有一个精灵为我指出了村子的方向
She literally only showed me the direction
她真的只是告诉我正确方向
and didn't give me any words of encouragement.
一句鼓励的话都没有说
As a child, I thought she was so coldhearted.
当时还是孩子的我心想 “这个人好冷血啊”
I don't know if you sensed my fear
不知道你是不是察觉到我的不安
or if you just did it on a whim, but…
还是只是一时兴起…
you showed me
你在我面前
the spell to create a field of flowers.
施展了变出花田的魔法
I thought it was beautiful.
我当时觉得好美
For the first time in my life, I thought magic was beautiful.
那是我人生中第一次觉得魔法好美
It's probably nothing but a coincidence,
虽然极可能纯属偶然
but the "stupid" spell that Master taught me
但我之所以能认识辛美尔他们
was what brought me together with Himmel and the crew.
正是因为有师父教给我的 这个“无聊”的魔法
Also, Serie,
还有一件事 赛丽艾
I'm sure you're planning on failing Fern as well,
你肯定也打算不让菲伦通过吧
but I don't think you can.
但多半是行不通的
She will exceed your expectations.
那孩子已经超出了你的想象
We've entered the era of humans.
人类的时代已经来临了
She will "exceed my expectations"?
超出了我的想象？
My mana has her paralyzed with fear.
明明都被我的魔力吓到动弹不得
She's the same as all the other examinees.
跟其他考生没什么两样嘛
Wait, what is it that you see?
等等 你…看到什么了？
It's unstable.
魔力在晃动
Your name is Fern, right?
你名字叫做菲伦吧？
Become my apprentice.
你来当我徒弟吧
What? No.
什么？我才不要
You won't regret it.
你不会后悔的
I will be able to take you to even greater heights.
我能引领你到达更高的境界
To a level which no other mage has ever reached.
是至今没有任何魔法使能企及的程度
Will that impact my result on this exam?
那会跟我这次考试的结果有关系吗？
Maybe it will.
可能有喔
I see.
这样啊
Mistress Serie…
赛丽艾大人…
Fern,
菲伦
I'm sure Serie is going to say this and that,
赛丽艾一定会滔滔不绝说个没完
but you don't need to listen to her demands.
但是你完全不用理会她的要求
Just as I will be failed no matter what I say to Serie,
正如我不管说什么 赛丽艾都不会让我合格
you will pass no matter what you say to her.
不管你说什么 你都一定会合格的
After all, Serie's instincts are always right.
毕竟赛丽艾的直觉从没出错过
I am Mistress Frieren's apprentice.
我是芙莉莲大人的弟子
You were advised by Frieren, huh?
芙莉莲事先提点过你了？
I'm not foolish enough to let a promising mage slip away.
我可没有笨到放走有潜力的魔法使
You pass.
你合格了
Next!
下一个！
See you again.
那么再见了
Subtitle translation by: Kiko Morita
字幕翻译：洪贞韵